<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Agony | jmcd.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmcd.github.io/blog/categories/agony/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmcd.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-28T08:25:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmcd.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John McDowall]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop It Nintendo, No, You're Hurting Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmcd.github.io/blog/2013/01/07/stop-it-nintendo-no-you're-hurting-me/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmcd.github.io/blog/2013/01/07/stop-it-nintendo-no-you&#8217;re-hurting-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the early nineties I bought a SNES with Super Mario World. You could go from a boxed console to playing a game in minutes - all you had to do was plug a few cables in.</p>

<p>Yesterday I got a Wii U. The setup process was so long winded and exasperating that it would make the calmest fanboy wonder whether there is any Nintendo employee with the responsibility of &ldquo;giving a fuck about user experience&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s like they have excellent low level developers, excellent game developers, but didn&rsquo;t think how they would plug everything together.</p>

<pre><code>INT. NINTENDO HQ, THE MOON

Game Devs: OK, were done with the new Mario game, it is sweeeet!
Sys Devs: Shut up guys - we're busy here busting our ass doing something important with a kernel and raster bliting. For all you know.
GD: You're jealous, wait till you see the new suit Mario has!
SD: ...
GD: It's the Super Acorn Flying Squirrel Suit!
SD: Jesus.
GD: When you get it, Mario has a tail and can glide and everything!
SD: Isn't that the exact same thing as the Raccoon suit from Super Mario Bros 3?
GD: IT'S SIMILAR BUT DISTINCT
SD: Oh, go on then, show us.
GD: If you would get a bend on and finish writing the system shell we would show you!
SD: The shell is YOUR responsibility FFS!
GD: But... we thought you were writing it...
SD: Oh man, we are fucked!
GD: Don't panic, don't panic, I think we have some garbage old Wii UI code on a thumb drive.
Manager: What's all this carry on, don't you know we launch in five days time?!
SD: Hi boss. We were just discussing how we were going to handle, err, handle ... system updates! Yes that sounds feasible.
M:  And how are they going to handle it?
SD: Through a massive non-delta patch downloaded at first boot of course!
M:  Excellent! One question though.
SD: Yes?
M:  "down" "load"?
SD: From the Internet.
M:  "inter"...
SD: You requestioned the bandwidth, right?
M:  Guys, I'm going home. This fine liquor isn't going to drink itself.
</code></pre>

<h2>System Update</h2>

<p>The box arrived at the office. I thought it a good idea to set it up and download any updates while I was at work, that way the machine would be ready to go by hometime. See? I am smart! The Wii U refused to connect to the WPA2 Personal network, even with security turned off. At the time I was disappointed to be denied updates until home, but it turned out I had dodged a bullet - a bullet made of progress bars and crazy.</p>

<p>Once safely ensconced in my Fortress Of Solitude, I assembled the system and successfully connected to the wifi in my flat.</p>

<p>GREAT! HERE WE GO! YES I WOULD LIKE TO UPDATE THANKYOU!</p>

<p>I was past the Rubicon. A warning message told me not to try anything funny with the power buttons, and I had heard scare stories of users who had bricked consoles by powering down during updates. I would just wait for that little progress bar to move along. Except it wasn&rsquo;t moving. It was stuck, with 0% progress. Through the power of concentration and scowling, I transmitted powerful brain signals to the Wii U that eventually made the progress bar move - HOORAY! HOORAY FOR PROGRESS BAR PROGRESS!</p>

<p>The progress bar on the Wii U is accompanied by a high pitched &ldquo;dididi dididi&rdquo; sound. The system update took almost two hours to download. You will probably want to turn the sound down or something.</p>

<p>The length of time the update took to download makes me think that either:</p>

<ul>
<li>This is a big download</li>
<li>Nintendo do not have bandwidth</li>
<li>This is a big download and Nintendo do not have bandwidth</li>
<li>So, probably a huge download of entirely new system software and firmware. Not a delta-update. Thanks.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Let&rsquo;s Play a Game!</h2>

<p>The console came bundled with Nintendo Land, but I didn&rsquo;t want to play that because it&rsquo;s for kids. I wanted to play the one where a cute cartoon plumber runs around a candy-cane world eating magic plants, so I headed to the &ldquo;eShop Channel&rdquo; to buy it online.</p>

<p>I am buying all my stuff without media now, because I am from the future.</p>

<p>Now I have bought the game and it has downloaded. HA, fooled you! I haven&rsquo;t, and it hasn&rsquo;t. I have to connect my Mii to my Nintendo Network Id first. Of course I do!</p>

<p>Do I have a Nintendo Network Id? Do I need to make a new one? I have one already, yes, I am certain. I used it years ago. I remember I would feverishly collect &ldquo;stars&rdquo; by registering purchases in order to claim prizes, which promised to be stuff like a gold Gameboy but turned out to be stuff like a JPEG of a mushroom playing football.</p>

<p>I go to my computer to see if I can remember my details. I can! I am so smart! Oh, but the Wii U says the details are bad. I investigate and find that I was entering the details for my &ldquo;Club Nintendo&rdquo; account, which is actually a different thing from a Nintendo Network Id. Boy did I feel stupid, but I guess anyone could make that mistake.</p>

<p>Wait - &ldquo;Club Nintendo&rdquo;, that rang a bell. My 3DS (I have a 3DS because I am cool) is always moaning at me to connect its eShop to my Club Nintendo account. Ergo, my 3DS has a Nintendo Network Id. I navigate the 3DS eShop and successfully link it to my Club Nintendo account. Now I just need to find my Nintendo Network Id. I can&rsquo;t find it. Maybe its my Mii friend sharing code? No, it isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>Turns out, my Club Nintendo account, 3DS eShop registration, friend code, previous Wii shop registration are all distinct entities, and none of them are a Nintendo Network Id. I have to create a new one. Stupid John, stupid stupid John. How could I not have known this?</p>

<p>I create a new Nintendo Network Id. All the glory of the eShop is mine. All these multiple accounts will be fine, so long as I remember the distinctions and security details and passwords for credit cards. No biggie.</p>

<p>I buy New Super Mario Bros Wii U. I love the name of this game. It is a name that is technically correct, the best kind of correct. The eShop tells me that I can view the progress of the download in the Download Manager. I in-expertly try to navigate to the Download Manager, tapping on many things that are not the Download Manager. It is at this point that it is apparent that programs take a long time to launch on the Wii U. Each program launch takes many seconds, and I am impatient. I can feel my life ending as I wait for the stupid program, that I didn&rsquo;t even want to load, to load.</p>

<p>Success! I have launched the Download Manager. &ldquo;Estimating Time Remaining&rdquo;. Tense. Wait for it. Ohhhhh, four hours?!</p>

<p>One of the cool things about the Wii U is that you can turn your TV onto another channel and waste your life watching some garbage like America&rsquo;s Next Top Dancing Glee Ice Sharks, and STILL monitor Wii U progress bars on the secondary baby screen. It&rsquo;s called science.</p>

<p>The progress bar chugs along for 20 minutes then disappears. &ldquo;Error&rdquo;. Error? &ldquo;Try downloading again later&rdquo;. Try later? How? There are no controls to retry or resume the download. In the end, it seems that the Wii U itself will try again later, so maybe those notes were for itself, so it would remember. The download restarts.</p>

<p>Several hours more pass, but it feels longer. Perhaps in the years that I have been waiting for downloads, the Wii U has been obsoleted by a flying XBox. Yes, probably.</p>

<p>The download completes. The Download Manager tells me that I must install the download before playing. I would like to ask the Download Manager why it doesn&rsquo;t just install the download for me, but it probably wouldn&rsquo;t understand, or would just tell me that it &ldquo;wasn&rsquo;t his department&rdquo;. I tap to install, and a while later I am the victor.</p>

<p>I go to the home screen, and tap the icon to start the game. It starts, and by &ldquo;starts&rdquo;, I mean it starts downloading an update.</p>

<p>NO FUCKING WAY NO WAY NO WAY?! That thing that I just downloaded? That multi-gigabyte blob transmitted through wet string? That was not the most up-to-date version?! It wasn&rsquo;t, and I endure another twenty minutes of downloading, followed by some minutes of updates.</p>

<p>(Other programs that are bundled with the console (YouTube, Netflix) also have available updates on first launch, even after you have applied the mega system update. This is literally incredible.)</p>

<p>I am finally into the game and it is pretty great. Pretty, pretty great.</p>

<h2>Wii System Transfer</h2>

<p>The Wii U is compatible with Wii software via the Wii channel. Turning on the Wii channel basically sets your Wii U into a Wii mode. The two modes are entirely segregated - there is no nice integration like having Wii channels show up on your Wii U home screen, or transfer of shop credits. It&rsquo;s full-on segregated emulation or simulation.</p>

<p>The Wii System Transfer lets me transfer stuff from a stupid old Wii to a fancy new Wii U. Stupid old Wii, what person would want you now?</p>

<p>Nintendo realize that is not a good idea to have too many people transferring data from old Wiis, because they would end up selling them at Cash Converters, and that would depress the price of new hardware. To this end, Nintendo have deliberately made the Wii System Transfer the most convoluted protocol possible, so as only the most perseverant soul will enjoy their Skyward Sword savegames on the Wii U.</p>

<p>Nintendo probably had a shortlist of protocols for performing the transfer.</p>

<ul>
<li>An ad-hoc network using custom protocol, à la AirDrop in OS X. &lt;&ndash; Too easy to use. REJECTED</li>
<li>Direct Bluetooth communication. &lt;&ndash; Customer might not have enough close power sockets to create bluetooth network. REJECTED</li>
<li>Detection of both devices on a common wifi network. &lt;&ndash; I like to steal my neigbours&#8217; wifi, this will cause problems. REJECTED</li>
<li>Secure upload of Wii data to a server on the Internet, download via key. &lt;&ndash; No, because&hellip; just because. REJECTED</li>
<li>An absolutely cuckoo bananas hybrid of Internet connectivity AND, unbelievably, SD card swapping. &lt;&ndash; WINNAR!</li>
<li>So they chose the last one. It&rsquo;s pretty crazy, but not quite crazy enough. To really make people dizzy Nintendo hit you with the channel download thing.</li>
</ul>


<p>To start the process off, there is a channel on the Wii U home screen. It is called Wii System Transfer. I launch this program and it explains some of the comically circuitous journey I am starting, it then tells me to download the Wii System Transfer program. I thought I was in the Wii System Transfer, because I launched a program with the same name? Stupid John. Stupid, stupid John.</p>

<p>I download the Wii System Transfer channel as instructed. I now have two channels called Wii System Transfer! With the same icon! One is the shell program, one is the actual program. They are distinguished by one having marquee style scrolling text.</p>

<p>I start the program. It has eight pages of steps explaining about the transfer and switching SD cards. I go through the pages, and insert the SD card. I dunno, I must have been drunk or something, because it turns these steps are not actually doing anything, they are just eight pages of explanations. D&#8217;oh. Stupid John. I finally get to the part where I prepare the SD card, and have to do things to the rubbish old Wii.</p>

<p>Now I have to download the Wii System Transfer program on the old Wii. The instructions tell me it&rsquo;s OK to turn off the Wii U if I don&rsquo;t have enough power sockets, but I pitty the souls who only have a single Wiimote, as they will have to unpair and pair the Wiimote as they switch system. I power up the old Wii. It&rsquo;s been a month or two since I used this machine, so it needs a system update. OK. I am numb now, so that is OK. I go to the eShop, find the program (it is scrolled off the bottom of the eShop home screen) install it, and transfer the data.</p>

<p>The process is especially crushing because it keeps saying &ldquo;Wii&rdquo; too much, and your brain starts to do that thing where repeated words don&rsquo;t make sense any more. Verbatim: &ldquo;Wii Points Transferred. 100 Wii Points have been transferred. You can use these Wii Points in the Wii Shop Channel on the target Wii U console&rsquo;s Wii Menu&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The actual transfer process is animated by those whimsical Pikmin carrying visual representations of your data to a rocket, then blasting off to a planet labeled &ldquo;Wii U&rdquo; - cute.</p>

<p>Now I have my Wii data on my Wii U. I am so smart. Wait! My Wii was one of the original ones with GameCube compatibility, that means that if I want to play Super Mario 64 I have to play it on, <em>shudder</em>, the classic controller! Nooooooooooo!</p>

<p>Fuck it, I&rsquo;ll just get my N64 out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
